A Guide to the Henkel Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8653-d
Henkel Family Papers 1800-1846
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8653-d
679 items
Mrs. John Godfrey Miller, in memory of John Godfrey Miller
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research
Acquisition Information
This material was given to the Library on December 9, 1986, by Mrs. John Godfrey Miller of New Market, Virginia, through Dr. H.E. Comstock of Winchester, Virginia, in memory of John Godfrey Miller.
Scope and Content
This collection of 679 items (3 Hollinger boxes, 1 linear shelf foot), 1800-1846, and undated, consists chiefly of the correspondence and business accounts of Dr. Solomon Henkel(1777-1847) of New Market, Virginia, who served as physician, pharmacist, printer, and postmaster of New Market and surrounding areas of the Shenandoah Valley.
Letters relating primarily to Solomon Henkel's medical and pharmaceutical practice have been grouped together, except for his accounts and correspondence with Bryan, Hampson & Company, Henry Keerl and Sons, Druggists, G.W. and John George Bottler, Druggists, and Matthias Kin, plant and seed merchant, who all have their own folders.
Items of note among Solomon Henkel's medical correspondence include: two letters from Dr. Henry Evans, one requesting instructions on making an "electrifying machine," perhaps used with quicksilver as a medical treatment (March 29, 1810), and a second asking for directions for fixing the "notes" on his new guitar as there were no guitars close by (July 8, 1810); another requests that Henkel pay his account with Philadelphia paper notes as "Southern notes seldom pass at Northern banks" (April 15, 1803); and several persons writing to Henkel asking him to accept them as medical students (August 18, 1813; August 9, 1815; & August 29, 1823).
Solomon Henkel's medical correspondence and accounts furnish insight into the diagnostic tools, medicines, and treatment available for the use of the pioneer physician.
Solomon Henkel also had a great deal of correspondence concerning his printery and bookselling business dealing with purchases, sales, printing arrangements, book and pamphlet orders, subscriptions and accounts due. Two correspondents, Jacob Sherrer and Daniel Sherer, write almost exclusively about the book business, although Jacob Sherrer also describes his travels in Virginia and the activities of the communities he visits.
The Henkel family members represented in this collection include Solomon Henkel's Uncle Moses Henkel, Gideon Henkel, Silas Henkel, Jesse Henkel, Ambrose Henkel, Saul Henkel, Moses Henkel, Jr., and David Henkel, Solomon Henkel's brother.
Topics of interest include: a discussion of a smallpox vaccine and an heretical preacher, Mr. Willey (August 17, 1802); Gideon Henkel offering his services to Solomon Henkel in his proposed general merchandise business and later to sell medicines on commission (November 20, 1810; & February 15, 1816); Joel Henkel's involvement in the commissary business for the United States Army going to Detroit and a description of the reaction of the local people to General Hull's surrender of Detroit in August (October 27, 1812); competition from a new press in Springfield wishing to reprint some of Solomon Henkel's own works, missionary efforts among the Indians and the conversion of a noted Jewish Rabbi, disagreement between Paul Henkel and Moses Henkel over Christian behavior and doctrinal differences between Methodists and Lutherans (February 21 & 28; April 12 & December 25, 1819). Moses Henkel generally writes concerning religious topics, translations, and his articles written for Solomon Henkel's printery.
David Henkel's correspondence describes "The Objections of Tennessee of the Committee Against The Constitution of the General Synod" (December 21, 1821); recounts his travels and expositions about doctrine (n.d.); book sales (November 3, 1819); and discussion of the Methodists (January 27, 1817); and includes expositions regarding miracles and other religious topics (May 30, 1813).
The miscellaneous correspondence contains letters concerning Lutheran theology, doctrine, conferences, meetings, and other activities, and behavior. Many of these correspondents are Lutheran ministers and three of them, John Drehr, J.K. Rebenack, and George H. Riemenschneider, have been foldered separately.
Individual topics of interest include: several letters concerning Solomon Henkel's role as postmaster (February 27, 1811; March 31, 1814; and March 23, 1815); the possibility of the unification of the Lutheran denomination with the Presbyterians through the adoption of a common catechism (February 26, 1812) and the Episcopalians with the resolution of differences over the priesthood and ordination (July 16, September 16, and October 14, 1818); denominational rivalry, especially between the Baptists and Lutherans (December 3, 1815); Daniel Bryan asking support for his election to the Virginia Legislature(March 25 & 27, 1818); a request for help in securing type for a small handpress to be used at Union Seminary[ Tennessee] (April 17, 1819); a special conference on provincial religion (June 19, 1810); the visiting preacher Mr. Henkel (August 29, 1818); a printed circular concerning charity (October 30, 1817); and family behavior (October 30, 1816).
Organization
This collection has been arranged into four series: 1) Medical and Pharmaceutical Material, 2) Henkel Printery and Bookselling Business, 3) Henkel Family Correspondence, and 4) Miscellaneous Correspondence and Materials. It is in chronological order.
Container List
- SERIES I: MEDICAL & PHARMACEUTICAL MATERIAL
  - Correspondence of Solomon Henkel re his medical and pharmaceutical practice, 1803-1823 & n.d.; (4 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Account of Solomon Henkel with Bryan Hampson & Company, 1810-1822 & n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Account of Solomon Henkel with Henry Keerl & Sons, Druggists of Baltimore, 1813-1823; (2 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - G.W. and John George Bottler, Druggists, to Solomon Henkel, 1803-1815 (Box Box 1)
  - Matthias Kin, plant and seed merchant of Philadelphia, to Solomon Henkel, 1812-1815 (Box Box 1)
- SERIES II: HENKEL PRINTERY & BOOKSELLING BUSINESS
  - Correspondence of Solomon Henkel re the Henkel printery business and booksellers, 1809-1823 & n.d.; (4 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Daniel Sherer to Solomon Henkel, 1816-1823 (Box Box 2)
  - Jacob Sherrer to Solomon Henkel, 1811-1819 & n.y. (Box Box 2)
- SERIES III: HENKEL FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
  - Letters of David Henkel, 1813-1821 (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence from members of the Henkel family to Solomon Henkel, 1800-1821, 1845-1846 & n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 2)
- SERIES IV: MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE & MATERIALS
  - Letters from John Barnett to Solomon Henkel, 1813-1821 (Box Box 3)
  - Letters from John Dreher to Solomon Henkel, 1811-1819 (Box Box 3)
  - Letters from J.K. Rebenack to Solomon Henkel, 1809-1816 (Box Box 3)
  - Letters from Rev. George H. Riemenschneider to Solomon Henkel, 1809-1823 (Box Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1801-1825, 1844 & n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Material, n.d. (Box Box 3)